Finding Aid for Robert P. Ball Papers 1936-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert P. Ball Papers
1936-1998
1943-1998
Ball, Robert P., 1926-
European correspondent for Time and Fortune magazines, 1945-1985. Letters to his parents concerning in part his student life at the University of Michigan in the 1940s, his war-time experiences as a naval officer in the Pacific theatre during World War II, and his career as a journalist in Europe from the late 1940s to the mid-1970s; student writings; dispatches written for Time and Fortune; and photographs.
87445 Aa 2
14 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Robert P. Ball (donor no. 7467 ) and came to the library in July-August 1987.
The collection is open for research.
Robert Ball, born June 18, 1926 in Owosso, Michigan, enjoyed a long and productive career as European correspondent for Time and Fortune magazines from 1954 to 1985. Ball's education included two stints at the University of Michigan interrupted by a tour of duty with the United States Navy during World War II. Ball left the English Ph.D. program in 1949 to pursue his interest in journalism. He traveled around Europe in 1950 and supported himself by selling a series of articles on the European common man to Michigan newspapers. Ball next worked as press officer for the United States High Command for Germany; he held this position until he caught on as a stringer for Time in September 1954.
Ball's career at Time was a study in steady advancement in status and responsibility: Munich stringer, 1954; Bonn bureau staffer, 1957; London deputy bureau chief, 1962; European Economic Correspondent, 1975. He covered the uprisings in Hungary and Poland in 1956; the Berlin Crises, 1958-1961; the Profumo Affair of 1963; the European Common Market from 1962 to 1970; and the Czechoslovakia revolt in 1968. Given the economic bent of Ball's beat, it was not surprising that Fortune hired him as European editor and correspondent. He covered business, industry, and enterprise for Fortune magazine until his retirement in June 1985. Upon his retirement, Ball organized his papers in preparation for writing a book on his journalistic experiences.
The Robert Ball papers are roughly divided into two subgroups according to the focus of material, personal or professional. Within this framework, the personal papers are arranged in series by type then by chronological order. The professional papers are arrayed in strict chronological order regardless of type, except for the cassette tapes which stand as a distinct series. Ball's organization of the materials in binders both necessitated and facilitated strict adherence to chronology in ordering the professional papers. The researcher should note that the division of materials into personal and professional groups can not be absolute given the dual nature of reportorial writing. Such writing is both personal and professional. Some blurring of the categories is evident, especially for the years 1948 to 1951 when Ball's nascent career did not permit rigid distinctions to be drawn in the materials.
Subjects:
Ball, Robert P., 1926-; Europe.; Fortune.; Journalists--United States.; Time.; United States. Office of the US High Commissioner for Germany.; University of Michigan--Students--Correspondence.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ball, Robert P., 1926-; Graduation ceremonies.; Seamen.; United States. Navy.
Subjects: Sound Recordings
Ball, Robert P., 1926-; Journalists--United States.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Personal Papers
  Personal Papers (1.5 linear feet, 1936-1962) is composed of three main subseries: Correspondence, Education, and Newspaper Clippings. There are also some photographs.
  - Photographs, 1943-1950 (Box 1)
    (includes portrait, snapshot of commencement address, and photos of Ball with other people)
  - Correspondence, September 1936-1976; 41 folders (Box 1)
    The bulk of the Personal Papers series is comprised of Correspondence (0.75 linear feet, 1936-1974). Most of the correspondence is addressed to Ball's father and mother although there are business letters interspersed in the years 1948 to 1954. Topics of the letters include student life at the University of Michigan during the 1940s, his war-time experiences as a naval officer in the Pacific theater, and his life as an American in Europe from the late-1940s to the mid-1970s. His mother evidently transcribed Ball's overseas missives to forward to Adele Ball. The transcripts were only retained if Ball's original letter was missing. The correspondence is arranged chronologically
  - Education
    Education (0.5 linear feet, 1933-1949) centers on his years as a student and is comprised mainly of his writings. The series documents his early writing style and world-view, especially in the papers from Owosso High School and the University of Michigan essays. Also included are drafts from a historical novel that he never finished, "The Cock and the Cross," about the plague and the Swiss Reformation.
    - Awards and honors, 1943-1949 (Box 2)
    - Writings, circa 1933-1949
      - Emerson Elementary School, circa 1933-1935 (Box 2)
      - Owosso High School, 1941-1943; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - University of Michigan, 1943-1949
        - Budgets and diary, 1943-1945 (Box 2)
        - Essays, 1947-1949 (Box 2)
        - Poetry, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
        - Stories, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
      - Vacation Travelog "Around Europe on Two Wheels,", 1947-1948 (Box 2)
      - Unfinished Historical Novel, "The Cock and the Cross,", 1948-1949; 2 folders (Box 2)
        (draft with corrections)
      - Unfinished Historical Novel, "The Cock and the Cross,", 1948-1949 (Box 2)
        (notebooks)
      - European Notebooks, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    The last subseries in the Personal Papers series is Newspaper Clippings (0.25 linear feet, 1941-1962). The earlier clippings are about Ball, while the later clippings are both about Ball and by Ball. The section includes articles Ball wrote while on his first tours of Europe.
    - 1941-1946 (Box 2)
    - European bicycle tour, 1947-1948 (Box 2)
    - European "Common Man", 1950; in ledger (Box 2)
    - 1951-1962 (Box 2)
- Professional Papers
  Professional Papers (13.25 linear feet, 1951-1998) is the second series in the collection. It includes two subseries: United States High Commission for Germany and Time and Fortune Magazine Correspondent.
  - United States High Commission for Germany, 1951-1954
    The United States High Commission for Germany (0.25 linear feet, 1951-1954) subseries includes memos, press releases, and reports generated by Ball in his capacity as press officer.
    - Memos and Reports, 1951-1954; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Press Releases, 1952-1953; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Time and Fortune Magazine Correspondent
    The majority of the collection is in the Time and Fortune Magazine Correspondent section (12 linear feet, 1954-1998). It includes a set of cassette tapes of interviews conducted by Ball for Fortune Magazine, mainly with executives of European automobile companies, dispatches for Time and Fortune, and a brief record of his expenses.
    The dispatches for Time and Fortune are arranged chronologically, in the binders as they were stored by Ball. The subject headings were created by him as well. The bulk of the materials consists of on-the-spot reports cabled to Time or Fortune and drafts of articles for the magazine. Also included is correspondence with editors and sources and records of his expenses. The articles for Time include both political and economic topics, while the articles for Fortune are predominantly economic.
    - Professional correspondence, 1958-1991 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Recordings of Interviews for Fortune, 1975-1983
      (cassette tapes)
      - Edwards, Mike, CEO, BL Cars, 1975 (Box 2)
      - Sixth International University for Presidents (Athens), 1975; 2 audiocassettes (Box 2)
      - Eurocommunism. (Amendola), 1978; 2 audiocassettes (Box 2)
      - Zahn, CEO, Daimler-Benz, 1978; 2 audiocassettes (Box 2)
      - Hahn, CEO, Volkswagen, 1982 (Box 2)
      - Prinz Gerhard, CEO, Daimler-Benz, 1982 (Box 2)
      - Leutwiler, Fritz, Swiss National Bank, 1983; 2 audiocassettes (Box 2)
      - Pohl, Karl Otto, German Bundesbank, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Dispatches for Time (by topic), 1954-1970
      - Bavaria, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Satellites, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
      - Zhukov, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
      - Malenkov Resignation, 1955 (Box 3)
      - Khruschev, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
      - Communist Party Soviet Union 20th Congress, 1956 (Box 3)
      - Destalinization, 1956 (Box 3)
      - Hungary, 1956 (Box 3)
      - Po, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
      - Mikoyan, 1957 (Box 3)
      - Satellites, 1957 (Box 3)
      - Soviet Bloc, 1957 (Box 3)
      - Khruschev, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
      - Sputnik, 1958 (Box 4)
      - Khruschev, 1958 (Box 4)
      - Scandinavia, 1958 (Box 4)
      - Berlin Crisis, 1958-1959 (Box 4)
      - Germany, 1959-1960 (Box 4)
      - Germany, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
      - Berlin Wall, 1961 (Box 4)
      - Germany, 1961-1962 (Box 5)
      - Britain, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
      - European Common Market, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
      - Britain, 1963 (Box 5)
      - Profumo Affair, 1963 (Box 5)
      - Britain, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
      - MacMillan Resignation, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
      - Britain, 1964 (Box 6)
      - AT&T Cover, 1964 (Box 6)
      - Cyprus, 1964 (Box 6)
      - Economics, 1964 (Box 6)
      - Wilson Government, 1964 (Box 6)
      - Khruschev Out, 1964 (Box 6)
      - Britain, 1964-1965 (Box 7)
      - Churchill funeral, 1965 (Box 7)
      - Common Market, 1965 (Box 7)
      - Currencies, 1965-1966 (Box 7)
      - Common Market, 1965-1966 (Box 7)
      - Common Market, 1966 (Box 7)
      - East Europe, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
      - Germany, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
      - Common Market, 1967 (Box 8)
      - Kennedy Round, 1967 (Box 8)
      - Pound Devaluation, 1967 (Box 8)
      - Gold, 1967 (Box 8)
      - Common Market, 1967-1968 (Box 8)
      - Currencies, 1967-1968 (Box 8)
      - Czechoslavakia, 1968 (Box 8)
      - Czech Aftermath, 1968-1969 (Box 8)
      - Common Market, 1968-1969 (Box 8)
      - Currencies, 1968-1969 (Box 8)
      - Gold, 1968-1969 (Box 8)
      - Currencies, 1969 (Box 9)
      - Common Market, 1969 (Box 9)
      - Germany, 1969 (Box 9)
      - Investors Overseas Services, 1969 (Box 9)
      - Germany, 1969-1970 (Box 9)
      - Common Market, 1969-1970 (Box 9)
      - Currencies, 1969-1970 (Box 9)
      - Investors Overseas Services, 1969-1970 (Box 9)
    - Dispatches for Time (by date), 1954-1970
      - 1954-1970, 10 folders (Box 14)
      - 1986-1998, 16 folders (Box 14)
      - 1955-1963 (Box 14)
        (miscellaneous)
    - Dispatches for Fortune, 1970-1985
      - Investors Overseas Services, 1970 (Box 10)
      - Edward Heath, 1971 (Box 10)
      - Hoffman-LaRoche, 1971 (Box 10)
      - Enlarged Common Market, 1971 (Box 10)
      - Volkswagen, 1972 (Box 10)
      - International Banking, 1972 (Box 10)
      - Henkel, 1972 (Box 10)
      - Time Inc. and Europe, 1972 (Box 10)
      - European Defense, 1972 (Box 10)
      - An Opening in Europe, 1972 (Box 10)
      - Jim Slater, 1973 (Box 10)
      - Antoine Riboud, 1973 (Box 10)
      - Europe's Foreign Workers, 1973 (Box 10)
      - Alliance, 1973 (Box 10)
      - Britain's Troubles, 1974 (Box 10)
      - Lord Cowdray, 1974 (Box 10)
      - Michelin, 1974 (Box 10)
      - Italy, 1974 (Box 10)
      - European Auto Industry, 1975 (Box 10)
      - Portugal, 1975 (Box 10)
      - Britain's Nationalized Industries, 1975 (Box 10)
      - An American Look at German Science, 1976 (Box 10)
      - Mit Bestimmung, 1976 (Box 10)
      - State of Europe, 1976 (Box 11)
      - Guest, Keen, and Nettlefolds, 1976 (Box 11)
      - Britain, 1977 (Box 11)
      - France, 1977 (Box 11)
      - Zahn, 1977 (Box 11)
      - Nestle, 1977 (Box 11)
      - North Sea Oil, 1978 (Box 11)
      - German Economy, 1978 (Box 11)
      - Whither Europe, 1978 (Box 11)
      - British Ley, 1978 (Box 11)
      - European Capitalism, 1978 (Box 11)
      - Leutwiler, 1978 (Box 11)
      - Peugeot-Citroen-Chrysler, 1978 (Box 11)
      - Flick, 1978 (Box 11)
      - Thatcher, 1979 (Box 11)
      - Eurocommunism, 1979 (Box 11)
      - Volkswagen, 1979 (Box 11)
      - NATO, 1979 (Box 11)
      - Swiss Watch Industry, 1979 (Box 11)
      - Iran Financial Fallout, 1979 (Box 11)
      - Getty Estate, 1980 (Box 11)
      - Airbus, 1980 (Box 11)
      - B.M.W., 1980 (Box 12)
      - Liebherr, 1980 (Box 12)
      - European Management, 1980 (Box 12)
      - European Retailing Invasion, 1980 (Box 12)
      - Labor Party, 1980 (Box 12)
      - NATO, 1980-1981 (Box 12)
      - Roland W. Row, 1981 (Box 12)
      - Renault, 1981 (Box 12)
      - Pipeline, 1981 (Box 12)
      - Deutschebank, 1981 (Box 12)
      - Po, 1981 (Box 12)
      - Japan, 1981 (Box 12)
      - Europe's Misery, 1981 (Box 12)
      - Social Democrats, 1982 (Box 12)
      - Dow Europe, 1982 (Box 12)
      - Nuclear Arms, 1982 (Box 12)
      - Tetrapak, 1982 (Box 12)
      - Why Europeans Don't Think Like Us, 1982 (Box 12)
      - Korf, 1982 (Box 12)
      - Airbus, 1982 (Box 12)
      - Germany, 1982 (Box 12)
      - Nestle, 1982 (Box 12)
      - Prinz, Mercedes-Benz, 1982 (Box 12)
      - Mercedes-Benz, 1982 (Box 13)
      - Leutwiler, Swiss National Bank, 1982 (Box 13)
      - Olivetti, 1982-1983 (Box 13)
      - Fohker, 1983 (Box 13)
      - French Protectionism, 1983 (Box 13)
      - German Election, 1983 (Box 13)
      - Japanese Investment, 1983 (Box 13)
      - Thatcher, 1983 (Box 13)
      - Volkswagen, 1983 (Box 13)
      - Ruhrgas, 1983 (Box 13)
      - Deutsche Bundesbank, 1983 (Box 13)
      - Sweden, Gyllenhamer, 1983 (Box 13)
      - Common Market, 1983 (Box 13)
      - German Electronics, 1983 (Box 13)
      - Bellisario, 1984 (Box 13)
      - British Unions, 1984 (Box 13)
      - Commerzbank Bounces Back, 1984 (Box 13)
      - East Bloc Debts, 1984 (Box 13)
      - Europe's Ablest Managers, 1984 (Box 13)
      - Why Europe's Outlook Has Brightened, 1984 (Box 13)
      - European Currency Unit, 1984 (Box 13)
      - Moussa, 1984 (Box 13)
      - Fiat, 1984 (Box 13)
      - Mercedes, 1984 (Box 13)
      - Bonn Spy Scandal, 1985 (Box 13)
      - Mandela March, 1985 (Box 13)
      - South African Debt Talks, 1985 (Box 13)
      - Mitterand Press, 1985 (Box 13)